A Guide to the Papers of Hugh Lee Butler 1896-1953
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Hugh Lee Butler 1896-1953
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 58
3 Hollinger Document Cases
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions..
Acquisition Information
Gift of "Hap" Forrest White, January 9, 1985
Biographical/Historical Information
Hugh Lee Butler, son of Le Grande Cornelius Butler and Martha Watkins Simpson Butler (d. 1897), was born July 19, 1871 in Farmville, Prince Edward County, Virginia. He had three brothers: Percy H., Hunter C. (d. 1905), and Stanley W. (d. 1923). Butler's parents moved to Norfolk when he was nine years old. He attended public schools in Farmville and Norfolk.
Butler married Effie Lee Grace, at the residence of W. E. Brown. The ceremony was performed by the Rev. J. T. Whitley. They became the parents of one daughter, Alice, and three sons, Hugh Lee Jr., Willard H., and Robert T., all of whom survived him. His wife died on December 17, 1935.
Butler began as an office boy at the Seaboard Air Line Railway on May 12, 1884. Promotion followed promotion over the years. In 1922, he was promoted to the position of contracting freight agent, a position he held until his retirement. On March 19, 1937, he received a congratulatory letter from L. R. Powell and Col. Henry W. Anderson upon completion of 50 years' service to the Seaboard. G. B. Rice presented him a 50- year service medal on behalf of the company. He retired at age 70, the Seaboard being the only company for which he had ever worked.
Butler's political career was a distinguished one. It began on what was known as the Common Council, July 1, 1902, representing Brambleton. His term as a member of the Norfolk City Council expired August 31, 1938, after 36 years of service.
He began his career as a member of the Charter Commission in 1902 and served on that body and the Select Council until the council-city manager form of government became a reality. Then he served as a member of the new government for 20 years. He also served on such committees as: Finance, Fire, Public Improvement and Annexation. He served many times as a member of the Democratic Committee from Brambleton and as chair of the Local Draft Board No. 1 from April 1, 1917 - March 31, 1919. He became especially involved in responding to citizens whose need for municipal services had not been met and civil servants (teachers, municipal workers) whose salaries had been cut during the Depression. Members of the Afro-American community found him to be a champion for their causes. One evidence of his tie to that community was a note from P. B. Young, publisher of the Afro-American Journal and Guide when Butler's wife died. He also worked on such projects as the introduction of parking meters to Norfolk and a study of school needs, both salaries as well as space.
Butler was known as a person of personal integrity, one who was loyal in his support of the city's welfare and one who had a mastery of the city's business. These traits provide a partial explanation as to the length of his political career. His service of 36 years was the longest in Norfolk's modern history. An appraisal of his life was best expressed in a resolution passed by the City Council on February 5, 1946: "That in the death of Hugh L. Butler, the citizens of Norfolk have lost a faithful and conscientious public servant, whose interest in their welfare and efforts in their behalf will long be remembered, and the City has lost a valued citizen of outstanding integrity and fidelity."
Though he retired from public office in 1938, he continued as a public servant. His appointment by President Franklin Delano Roosevelt on October 12, 1940, as Secretary to Norfolk City Draft Board No. 4 is just one instance of his service.
He was in demand as a speaker before such organizations as the Ballantine Civic Association and the Ocean View Democratic and Social Club. He was made an honorary member of the Norfolk Athletic Club.
He died at his home on January 28, 1946 following two heart attacks the previous week.
Scope and Content Information
The Butler Papers deal primarily with his duties on the Norfolk City Council from 1923-1938 as a representative of Brambleton (parking meters; race relations; Foreman Field; city anniversaries; Museum of Arts and Sciences; Blue Laws; study of schools); his service on the Local Draft Board from 1917-1922 (alleged draft evaders, delinquents, deserters); personal and family papers (tax returns, financial records, obituaries, condolences); pamphlets and brochures of Norfolk; clippings from Norfolk newspapers; and, a scrapbook.
Correspondence is arranged chronologically, or in original order as clipped together. Many carbons are on the backs of discarded "Seaboard Air Line Railway, Portsmouth, VA, Passing Report."
Arrangement
Correspondence is arranged chronologically, or in original order as clipped together.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Norfolk City Council and General
    - Councilman duties; Railroad Retirement Act; concerns of Afro-Americans; dedication of Foreman Field; city anniversaries; Norfolk Museum of Arts and Sciences Mar 10 1923 - Nov 20 1936 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Councilman duties; concerns of Afro-Americans; parking meter installation; Crime Prevention Conference; airport survey; 50-year Service Medal from Seaboard Air Line Railway Nov 21 1936 - Mar 25 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Councilman duties; parking meters; Blue Laws; Afro-American concerns Mar 26 1937 - May 29 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Councilman duties; Railroad Retirement Act; parking meters; Norfolk airport; "Union Mission" for Afro-Americans Jun 1 1937 - Oct 23 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Councilman duties; teachers' salaries; Police Dept.; Atlantic Coast Fleet; WPA project Oct 25 1937 - Mar 28 1938 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Councilman duties; Councilman election; Afro-American concerns; political address; WPA project Apr 1 1938 - Jun 23 1938 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Councilman duties; study of high schools; Norfolk Museum of Arts and Sciences; Hugh Lee Butler's retirement Jun 28 1938 - Aug 31 1939 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - World War I Draft Board Records
    - Draft Board Records for World War I; cases of alleged draft evaders, delinquents, deserters Dec 1 1917 - Apr 25 1922 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
- Work Records
  - Railroad Retirement Act (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
- Personal Papers
  - General Correspondence
    - Elks Memorial Services; invitations; acknowledgments; rental receipts Dec 6 1896 - Apr 21 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Family items; receipts, including rental receipts Apr 22 1937 - 1952 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Financial Records
    - Virginia and Norfolk tax returns for Hugh Lee Butler and Alice B Cruser 1939-1953 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Federal tax returns 1920-1941 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Family Obituaries and Condolences
    - Death of brother, Hunter C. Butler, Oct 4 1905; Death of brother, Stanley White Butler, Apr 1923; Death of wife, Effie Lee Grace Butler, Dec 17 1935 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
- Pamphlets and Brochures
  - Primary Norfolk and Tidewater Virginia (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous clippings from the: Public Ledger; Virginia and Pilot; Norfolk Landmark; Virginian-Pilot and the Norfolk Landmark; and, Times-Advocate. Includes 1922 election of Butler et al., picture of Butler; articles on Spanish-American War; and current events. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous clippings from the: Public Ledger; Virginia and Pilot; Norfolk Landmark; Virginian-Pilot and the Norfolk Landmark; and, Times-Advocate. Includes 1922 election of Butler et al., picture of Butler; articles on Spanish-American War; and current events. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5a)
  - Clippings from Norfolk newspapers. Includes Norfolk City unofficial / official election results (1922-1940); proposed charter change; editorial re. Late Richard W Peatross; Draft Board appointments (including Butler) by President Franklin D. Roosevelt on Oct 12 1940. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings from Norfolk Virginian-Pilot, Sept 1 1939- Nov 3 1939, re. Beginning and progress of World War I. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clipping from Norfolk newspapers. Include death of Woodrow Wilson; 'Jim Crow' law effective Jun 13 1906. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clipping from Norfolk Newspapers. Include death of Woodrow Wilson; 'Jim Crow' law effective Jun 13 1906. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook
  Various clippings beginning about Apr 18 1897 from Public Ledger. Include poems; Civil War reports; current events; funeral of sister-in-law, Cassie Grace; deaths of mother, Mrs. Martha A (sic) Butler (1987) and brother, Hunter C Butler (1905).
  - Scrapbook (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)